# XIN CHEN

University of Chinese Academy of Sciences | H: +86 186 1639 5193 | chenxin2@shanghaitech.edu.cn HomePage: chenxin.tech | GitHub | Google Scholar

### ABOUT ME

I'm a Researcher Scientist T10 at Tencent, working with Dr. Gang Yu for Generative AI. I obtained my Ph.D. from Chinese Academy of Sciences, advised by Prof. Jingyi Yu. Before that, I was supervised by Prof. Youyi Zheng at ShanghaiTech University, working on 3D modeling.

My research interests focus on Computer Vision for Graphics. I have a great passion on new things and new ideas, my goal is to create Generative AI which is about humans, used for humans, and benefits humans.

# RESEARCH INTERESTS

• Generative AI Multi-modal Language Models 3D AIGC

Computer Vision Human Performance Capture Motion Synthesis View Synthesis
 Computer Graphics Image-based Modeling Neural Avatar Neural Rendering

#### **EDUCATION**

Ph.D Degree, Computer Science 2018-2022

University of Chinese Academy of Sciences

Master Student, Computer Science 2016-2018

ShanghaiTech University

**B.Sc, Electronic Information Science** Rank: 1/172 2012-2016

Qingdao University of Technology

### Experience

Conference/Journal ReviewerCVPR, ICCV, AAAI/ TPAMI, TIP, IJCV, TMM, ...Jan. 2020 to PresentResearch ScientistTencent - QQ Image LabFeb. 2022 to PresentResearch Scientist InternTencent - Youtu LabDec. 2020 to Mar. 2021

# **Projects**

• 3D AIGC for Digital Avatar and Textured Mesh.

Feb. 2022 to Present

Proposed a text-to-texture framework for creating diverse avatar appearances and a text-to-shape model, Michelangelo, to generate 3D objects using diffusion models. Accepted to NeurIPS'23.

- Human Motion Generation via Language/Diffusion Models. Feb. 2022 to Present Introduced MotionGPT, a unified motion-language model to learn the semantic coupling and generate both motions and languages on multiple motion tasks. Accepted to NeurIPS'23. Presented Motion-Latent-Diffusion, a fast and high-quality motion diffusion model. Accepted to CVPR'23.
- Human Shape/Motion Reconstruction for Clothed Avatars.
   Dec. 2018 to Apr. 2022
   Built a Dome System using 80 cameras for multi-view stereo. Proposed a GAN-based scheme for human reconstruction, clothing segmentation, and virtual fitting, using non-rigid deformation for alignment. Lead the reconstruction project, 1000+ clothed humans, accepted to SIGGRAPH'22. Lead the MoCap project. Collected a sports motion dataset in diving, boxing, and more. Published on IJCV'21.
- Image-based Shape Generation. Aug. 2017 to Aug. 2018 Introduced a fully automatic framework with the learning-based instance semantic segmentation part and the graphics-based reconstruction part. Published on TVCG'18 (Graphics journal).
- Early R&D Projects. Before Aug. 2017
   Mobile Virtual Fitting. A single-view human body estimation and virtual fitting on Android in Realtime. Based on the front-facing RGBD camera (ToF). A Linear Blend Skinning (LBS) body model.
   Dynamic 4D Mesh Player. Stand-alone development work for free-view browsing on 4D scans, which supports mesh rendering, free-angle viewpoint change, and Poisson Surface Reconstruction.
   Gesture Interaction in VR. A two-hand controller. Leap Motion, HTC Vive for hardware support.

# SELECTED Publications (complete list...)

About 30 papers, over 10 as first/co-first author(\*) or project leader (†), 5000+ GitHub Stars in total.

- Paint3D: Paint Anything 3D with Lighting-less Texture Diffusion Models.
   Xianfang Zeng\*, Xin Chen\*, Zhongqi Qi\*, Wen Liu, Zibo Zhao, Zhibin Wang, Bin Fu, Gang Yu
   [Arxiv'23 | Project | Code | Paper | Github Stars 400+]
- AppAgent: Human Motion as a Foreign Language. Chi Zhang\*, Zhao Yang\*, Jiaxuan Liu\*, Yuchen Han, **Xin Chen**, Zebiao Huang, Bin Fu, Gang Yu [Arxiv'23 | Project | Code | Paper | Github Stars 3k+]
- LL3DA: Visual Interactive Instruction Tuning for Omni-3D Understanding, Reasoning, and Planning. Sijin Chen, Xin Chen<sup>†</sup>, Chi Zhang, Mingsheng Li, Gang Yu, Hao Fei, Hongyuan Zhu, Jiayuan Fan, Tao Chen. [Arxiv'23 | Project| Code | Paper]
- M3DBench: Let's Instruct Large Models with Multi-modal 3D Prompts.
   Mingsheng Li, Xin Chen†, Chi Zhang, Sijin Chen, Hongyuan Zhu, Fukun Yin, Gang Yu, Tao Chen.
   [Arxiv'23 | Project | Code| Paper ]
- Chartllama: A multimodal llm for chart understanding and generation.
   Yucheng Han\*, Chi Zhang\*, Xin Chen, Xu Yang, Zhibin Wang, Gang Yu, Bin Fu, Hanwang Zhang
   [Arxiv'23 | Project | Code | Paper]
- MotionGPT: Human Motion as a Foreign Language.
   Biao Jiang\*, Xin Chen\*, Wen Liu, Jingyi Yu, Gang Yu, Tao Chen
   NeurIPS'23 | Project | Code | Paper | Github Stars 1k+
- Michelangelo: Conditional 3D Shape Generation based on Shape-Image-Text Aligned Latent Representation.

Zibo Zhao, Wen Liu, **Xin Chen**, Xianfang Zeng, Rui Wang, Pei Cheng, Bin Fu, Tao Chen, Gang Yu, Shenghua Gao [NeurIPS'23 | Project | Code | Paper | Github Stars 100+]

- Executing your Commands via Motion Diffusion in Latent Space.
   Xin Chen\*, Biao Jiang\*, Wen Liu, Zilong Huang, Bin Fu, Tao Chen, Jingyi Yu, Gang Yu
   [CVPR'23 | Project | Code | Paper | Github Stars 400+]
- End-to-End 3D Dense Captioning with Vote2Cap-DETR.
   Sijin Chen, Hongyuan Zhu, Xin Chen, Yinjie Lei, Tao Chen, Gang Yu
   CVPR'23 | Video | Code | Paper
- A Large-Scale Outdoor Multi-modal Dataset and Benchmark for Novel View Synthesis and Implicit Scene Reconstruction.

Chongshan Lu, Fukun Yin, **Xin Chen**, Tao Chen, Gang Yu, Jiayuan Fan [ICCV'23 | Project | Code | Paper]

- TightCap: 3D Human Shape Capture with Clothing Tightness Field. Xin Chen, Anqi Pang, Peihao Wang, Wei Yang, Lan Xu, Jingyi Yu [SIGGRAPH'22 | Project | Code | Paper | TOG Journal Track]
- SportsCap: Monocular 3D Human Motion Capture and Fine-grained Understanding in Challenging Sports Videos.

Xin Chen, Anqi Pang, Yuexin Ma, Lan Xu, Jingyi Yu [IJCV'21 | Project | Code | Paper]

• ChallenCap: Monocular 3D Capture of Challenging Human Performances using Multi-Modal References.

Yannao He, Anqi Pang, **Xin Chen**, Han Liang, Yuexin Ma, Lan Xu [CVPR'21 Oral | Project | Paper]

- Anisotropic Fourier Features for Neural Image-Based Rendering and Relighting. Huangjie Yu, Anpei Chen, Xin Chen, Lan Xu, Ziyu Shao, Jingyi Yu
   [AAAI'22 Oral | Project | Paper]
- Few-shot Neural Human Performance Rendering from Sparse RGBD Videos.
   Anqi Pang\*, Xin Chen\*, Haimin Luo, Minye Wu, Jingyi Yu, Lan Xu
   [IJCAI'21 | Paper | Video ]

- Neural Free-Viewpoint Performance Rendering under ComplexHuman-object Interactions.
   Guoxing Sun, Xin Chen, Yizhang Chen, Anqi Pang, Pei Lin, Lan Xu, Jingya Wang, Jingyi Yu
   [ACMMM'21 | Paper | Video]
- Pose2Body: Pose-Guided Human Parts Segmentation.
   Zhong Li\*, Xin Chen\*, Wangyiteng Zhou, Yingliang Zhang, Jingyi Yu [ICME'19 Oral | Paper]
- AutoSweep: Recovering 3D Editable Objects from a Single Photograph.
   Xin Chen, Yuwei Li, Xi Luo, Tianjia Shao, Jingyi Yu, Kun Zhou, Youyi Zheng
   [TVCG'18 | Project | Code | Paper]
- Sparse Photometric 3D Face Reconstruction Guided by Morphable Models.
   Xuan Cao, Zhang Chen, Anpei Chen, Xin Chen, Shiying Li, Jingyi Yu
   [CVPR'18 | Paper | Video]

# References

Prof. Jingyi Yu Supervisor, IEEE Fellow ShanghaiTech University yujingyi@@shanghaitech.edu.cn Prof. Youyi Zheng Former Supervisor Zhejiang University youyi.zheng@zju.edu.cn